<!--<!DOCTYPE spec PUBLIC "DTDVersion-3" "../../support/dtd/v3m.dtd">-->
<spec rendered="9/16/2009 4:26:25 PM"><header><title>Glossary</title><version>0</version><date>9/16/2009</date></header><body><div1 id="glossary"><head>HL7 Glossary Additions</head><div2 id="glossary-POLB_DO000002UV"><head>POLB_DO000002UV Glossary</head><glist role="additionalterms"><gitem id="placer_order" lastEdit="2004-11-06T20:22:19"><label>Placer Order</label><def domainid="POLB_DO000002UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2004-11-06T20:22:19"><p>An order placed and maintained by a Placer system. Its status can only be changed by the placer. This must be in Request (RQO) mood</p></def></gitem><gitem id="occurrence_order" lastEdit="2004-11-06T20:22:01"><label>Occurrence Order</label><def domainid="POLB_DO000002UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2004-11-06T20:22:01"><p>An single instance of a recurring order. Each instance occurs at a specific point in time.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="filler_order" lastEdit="2005-12-31T15:57:38"><label>Filler Order</label><def domainid="POLB_DO000002UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2005-12-31T15:57:38"><p>An order created by a fulfiller. This may be in response to a Placer order which it seeks to fulfill or it may be initiated independently. These may also be in response to a paper order received by the Filler. These are always in the Promise (PRMS) Mood.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="recurring_order" lastEdit="2004-11-06T20:25:05"><label>Recurring Order</label><def domainid="POLB_DO000002UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2004-11-06T20:25:05"><p>An order for a series of requests to be performed over time.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="preliminary_report" lastEdit="2004-11-07T15:09:09"><label>Preliminary Report</label><def domainid="POLB_DO000002UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2004-11-07T15:09:09"><p>A preliminary report contains completed results that are valid for a point in time with the information currently available.  This report is not expected to be revised but may be replaced with a subsequent preliminary report or a final report..  The order remains active until a final report has been issued that sets the order and its components to 'completed'.    For example, a preliminary report for a blood culture reads 'no growth after 24 hours'; the order status remains active.  The final report of 'no growth after 7 days' is subsequently issued and the order status is set to 'completed'.   </p></def></gitem><gitem id="aliquot" lastEdit="2004-11-06T20:25:20"><label>Aliquot</label><def domainid="POLB_DO000002UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2004-11-06T20:25:20"><p>A portion of a specimen submitted for analysis. It may be scoped by the original specimen. An aliquot is a type of specimen in which, the player is a material taken as a sample from another pre-existing specimen (scoper). For example the part of a specimen on which a particular analysis is carried out.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="order_set" lastEdit="2004-11-06T20:24:46"><label>Order Set</label><def domainid="POLB_DO000002UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2004-11-06T20:24:46"><p>See Profile.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="profile" lastEdit="2004-11-06T20:22:42"><label>Profile</label><def domainid="POLB_DO000002UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2004-11-06T20:22:42"><p>A group of orderable items requested together as an ordering or billing convenience. These are generally configured on the requesting application and are expanded into order items before being sent to a fulfiller.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="result_revised" lastEdit="2004-11-06T20:24:00"><label>Result Revised</label><def domainid="POLB_DO000002UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2004-11-06T20:24:00"><p>A result that replaces a previously reported result that was not 'Complete'. The Revised result may have a 'Complete' status or may remain 'Active'</p></def></gitem><gitem id="isolate" lastEdit="2004-11-06T20:21:36"><label>Isolate</label><def domainid="POLB_DO000002UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2004-11-06T20:21:36"><p>A micro-organism on which observations are made. This may be obtained from a specimen submitted for analysis or it may be submitted in its own right. It may be scoped by the original specimen. An isolate is a type of specimen in which, the player is a culture of a type micro organism that has been isolated from other micro organisms and/or its source matrix. The scoping entity is the original specimen or culture.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="specimen" lastEdit="2004-11-06T20:24:23"><label>Specimen</label><def domainid="POLB_DO000002UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2004-11-06T20:24:23"><p>A sample obtained from a subject on which observations are performed. A specimen is a type of partitive role in which, the player is a material taken as a sample from a source scoping entity. For example, a specimen of venous blood taken from a patient for a laboratory investigation.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="result" lastEdit="2008-03-09T19:59:09"><label>Result</label><def domainid="POLB_DO000002UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2008-03-09T19:59:09"><p>A value obtained from an observation and reported against the appropriate Observation Act code. Results are in Event (EVN) mood</p></def></gitem><gitem id="result_partial" lastEdit="2004-11-06T20:23:46"><label>Result Partial</label><def domainid="POLB_DO000002UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2004-11-06T20:23:46"><p>A partial result refers to a multi-component result when some but not all components have been reported.  The order has not yet been fulfilled and is still active.  Each atomic result reported may be 'Active'  or 'Completed'.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="result_preliminary" lastEdit="2004-11-06T20:23:49"><label>Result Preliminary</label><def domainid="POLB_DO000002UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2004-11-06T20:23:49"><p>A result that is expected to be replaced with a revised result at a later stage. This result should be treated with a degree of caution as it is subject to change.  For example, a toxicology screen identifies the presence of an unidentified opiate.  This preliminary result is not set to completed and will be updated later with the specific drug and set to complete.  A preliminary result is not the same as a preliminary report.   See preliminary report.   </p></def></gitem><gitem id="result_corrected" lastEdit="2004-11-06T20:23:17"><label>Result Corrected</label><def domainid="POLB_DO000002UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2004-11-06T20:23:17"><p>A result that replaces a previously reported 'Complete' result.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="reference_change_value" lastEdit="2006-01-07T18:03:10"><label>Reference Change Value</label><def domainid="POLB_DO000002UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2006-01-07T18:03:10"><p>The Reference Change Value (formerly known as critical difference) is derived from the analytical and biological variability in the measured  parameters. It provides an estimate of the significance of change  between serial results and provides an index that will enable interpretation of results by the user or end user systems. Results  changes  &gt;= to the RCV of 0.99 probability are said to be "highly  significant", changes  &gt;= RCV at 0.95% probability but &lt;= to the RCV at  0.99 are said to be "significant".</p></def></gitem><gitem id="battery" lastEdit="2008-07-08T17:02:16"><label>Battery</label><def domainid="POLB_DO000002UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2008-07-08T17:02:16">A battery is a set of closely related observations. The components of a battery should have a generally accepted clinical,
functional or logical relationship to one another. In event mood a battery contains separate valued observations for
each of its subcomponents. In definition mood a battery defines a set of required and optional subcomponents. A request
for battery may be represented as a single observation in request mood with a code that refers to the defined set of
subcomponents.  Examples include blood pressure, complete blood count, chemistry panel.
</def></gitem><gitem id="rcv" lastEdit="2006-01-07T18:02:41"><label>RCV</label><def domainid="POLB_DO000002UV" sortkey="00" preferreddef="true"><p>See term <termref ref="reference_change_value">Reference Change Value</termref> instead.</p></def></gitem><gitem id="package" lastEdit="2004-11-06T20:25:17"><label>Package</label><def domainid="POLB_DO000002UV" sortkey="01" preferreddef="true" lastEdit="2004-11-06T20:25:17"><p>See Profile.</p></def></gitem></glist></div2></div1></body></spec>

